[Music]
hello everybody welcome to the centenary
century episode of ask a budget it's the
100th episode who would have imagined
that we would reach episode 100
so thank you all
for bringing us this far so let me see
who all is here i can see
svs chi-ching vijay jaidakshit
great to see you all and thank you for
being with me on this
century episode so first of all uh
apologies for yesterday's technical
problems in yesterday's live stream
there was some technical issue
everything was blurry and it was i was
not looking at the live chat so i had no
idea you guys were i know you were
trying to tell me something is wrong but
well so apologies for that i have uh
replaced the relevant hardware and
hopefully uh
today it will be
going fine
so yeah apologies for that and once
again thank you to all of thank you to
everybody all of you who have watched
the episode supported the channel in a
variety of way thank you for your
comments thank you for your questions
thank you for your support
for your support i would like to thank
all of the all of you who have put in
the time stamps i can think of akash
harshit rama lakshmi thank you so much
for doing that it's a it's been very
helpful very useful to me and to all the
viewers thank you so much for that
thank you to those of you who have
purchased memberships those of you who
have given donations paypal upi whether
it's one rupee 10 rupee or whatever it's
all valuable thank you so much i really
appreciate it and uh
so who would have imagined in less than
one year 100 episodes all live all
started on time
so it's been it's been quite a journey
and
it would not have been possible without
your viewership and your support if you
i would not have reached 10 episodes
let alone 100 if you had not been
watching it and asking questions if you
had not been watching it i would have
gone and done something else
right so it's all thanks to you so once
again thank you very much i really
appreciate
everything uh you know what they say
that if somebody gives you three seconds
of their time it's a privilege so for me
i've got so much of your viewership i am
i am truly blessed thank you very much
to all of you
right so with that said i'm gonna i've
taken a whole lot of questions and
hopefully i can answer as many of them
as possible let's start with the
question number one what is question
number one let's see
here we go oh okay all right
whoa whoa whoa okay okay i get it
okay okay
right
okay i get it this is a question that
i've been this is a demand a request
that has been
uh i have been getting every day every
week every month
so yes it is time for me to make an
announcement about this so
i have made many such announce i mean
many such uh
statements in the past that i will
create
course i will create what uh
documentaries i'll write books the thing
is if you have objectives if you have
goals they are simply
dreams unless you put a time limit a
deadline on them
so uh let me put a deadline on the book
now so my first episode of ask a widget
released went live on the 2nd of june
so on the 2nd of june this year
in a month's time i am going to release
a book
a book that will be a tightly focused
overview big picture overview of the
entirety of indian history it will cover
the last 70 000 years of indian history
and give you the one very clear specific
result that it will give you a proper
chronological account of what happened
in india and answer the big questions of
who are the indians what is their
history what is their origin what is
their culture civilization what are the
great achievements uh whatever
misfortunes befell the indian people and
so on and so forth all of that in one
book so this is going to be an e-book
initially
and it's going to be a tightly focused
book it's not going to be a 500 page
book it's going to be a quick brisk read
it's going to be an ebook i'm going to
release it on amazon kindle you can read
it on your phone tablet computer
wherever eventually i will release it as
a paper book as a yeah it's a physical
book you know the entire editorial
process is a long process there are
reviews and people give you
recommendations they ask you to change
things it's tedious time consuming there
is a good purpose for it obviously but
i will release it first with an ebook
and here's the deal
many of you many of us don't like
reading books so along with the ebook i
will also release in parallel a video
course
yeah tightly focused two three hour
video course a big picture overview of
the entirety of industry the past 70 000
years
of indian history it will not be on
youtube it will be on a different
platform it will be a paid course now
some of you will say why is it a paid
course i said that uh
information knowledge should always be
free
it's going to be a course that will
cover everything i've already covered on
the channel all the information is
already available on this channel there
are hundreds of videos i've answered
thousands of questions uh there are
hundreds of videos hundreds of hours of
watch time on my channel you can get all
the information for free i'm gonna just
put it together
record it again put it together into a
two three hour course video course and
i'm gonna place it on a different
platform which i will announce
when the time is right
the deadline is the second of june this
year um it gives me just a month to do
all this so that's a very tight deadline
but yeah unless you put a deadline
you're not going to achieve anything
right
so uh this is going to be a paid course
and a paid ebook obviously it's not
going to cost 10 000 rupees or even a
thousand rupees the course i will price
it at the price point of a pizza right
and there are two reasons why i'll
make it a paid course first of all
there's a psychological thing that if
you get something for free you don't
value it you know you don't use it it's
something that everybody has
it's just a psychological thing you may
get the best and most valuable
information and knowledge but if you get
it for free you don't value it but if
you have paid for it even a little bit
of money then you're gonna make sure
that you're gonna study it properly so
that's number one and secondly uh
by putting a small price on the course i
will make sure that the wrong people the
wrong audience stays away as you know on
this channel there are lots of people
who come just to
pass negative comments to to place
negative comments and to argue and
so on so forth so if you put a price on
the course
those people will stay away right so
that's that's the thing
so the target is
the 2nd of june
so
let's wish me luck
and
i i have some engagements this month i
have some traveling to do some public
appearances and all but i'm gonna try my
best to reach to to complete this task
by the second of june so if things go
well and i'm sure they will then by the
second of june you will have an ebook
and you will have a course you can
choose whichever
so that's the announcement and that's
the answer to this question now there's
a deadline and a time limit on this
thing
okay next question
anime and space edge pro anime says from
a reluctant youtuber to becoming a
regular one what
how has your youtube journey been you
mentioned you were an introvert was it
not for sports you would have spent most
of your time reading books what are your
thoughts on building such a big social
media connection
you are one of the most sought after
youtubers growing every day
and the second one is um
uh
compared to a budget in ask a budget
episode one what have we learned in this
journey of yours from episode one to
episode 100 about us your community
i have learned a lot i have learned a
lot about the community about the
youngsters of india the the interesting
thing is that um if i look at my google
analytics for my youtube channel it
shows me that the majority of my
audiences is less than 24 years old 24
or below so somehow i have been able to
connect with youngsters i mean i'm not a
youngster i'm in my 40s right i've got
gray hair as you can see but the
connection i have
accomplished is with kids with
youngsters which is fantastic
i could not could not have asked for
anything better so i have over the past
hundred episodes learned a great deal
about the
hopes desires aspirations ambitions
problems etc that youngsters in india
today have i know what they seek i know
what sort of information and knowledge
they seek i know what their aspirations
are they want to see india great
prosperous and they want to have a great
prosperous future they want to they all
want to contribute something to the
progress of the country
they are very interested in geopolitics
in history some of them in science as
well
there are lots of problems as well i get
lots of questions about resolving
various problems which i may not be the
best expert at you know but yeah i so i
have learned a lot about people i i've
realized that people want to be heard
everybody really wants to be heard
and everybody uh wants to do something
and wants to learn something there is a
genuine desire for learning
but not for the education system the
education system kills off everyone's
desire for learning but when information
is presented in a certain way maybe the
way i present it here people are
interested in it and people want to know
more i get thousands of questions every
week and i'm able to answer only a few
of them i try to you know select the
ones that represent everyone's questions
the best
so i have learned a lot over this time
it's been a great experience a great
learning experience i've understood the
world better the country better and for
me also i've understood myself better
it's been a growing experience i mean
i have realized that i personally am
capable of a certain amount of
consistency hard work i always
unless i was once or twice ill like
genuinely
that i was always i never missed an
episode i always came up on time
and i once uh realized the things a few
things
about myself such as
there is a certain comfort zone that i
have now reached on this channel i am
very comfortable doing this q and a
session this q a thing in format and all
that and i've not quite gone into the
other directions that i would have
wanted to so i need to break free from
this comfort zone and do something
different so these that's a it's a
growing process a learning process
there's a lot to learn it's uh the
journey has actually just begun it's not
even one year so i've learned a lot and
it's all thanks to you without your uh
viewership without your support with
that without your engagement i would
have learned none of these things and i
would not have been able to offer
anything to any of you so it's all
thanks to the audience to all of you
that this has been possible so thank you
very much
uh tech intern says do you prepare for
the answer before making any video
you know i get these i mean what i do is
typically a couple of days one or two
days before the live live stream happens
this q a livestream ask about visual
library one or two days before that i
select as many questions as i can which
i think will be useful and valuable to
the broadest possible audience
and then i just put them aside or the
questions
should be like questions that interest
me as well so i pick a whole bunch of
questions maybe 50 or so questions and i
and i select those
and you know if i were to go through
every question and prepare answers for
each question i would i would do nothing
else in my life
so i just pick a bunch of questions that
i find interesting and i'm sure that the
audience will gain some value and some
benefit from them and then i just come
here and answer them live as if i'm
having a conversation with somebody i
never prepare for prepare the answers
sometimes i keep the maps thing open and
i show some things on maps and all that
but you know i
if i were to start preparing
every answer beforehand i would do
nothing else in my life and i would not
be able to do anything else so no i
don't prepare any answers it's all
extempore it's all live here on the spot
whatever comes to my mind i say it
and that's that's how i do it
tedious says do you have any degree in
history or are you just a history
enthusiast is it possible to get mastery
in a subject by simply by self-study or
without getting a degree you know what i
don't have any degree in history
all of you are learning history from a
guy who doesn't have a history degree
oh my god how terrible is that
so that's what it is i don't have any
degree in history none whatsoever zero
zero degrees in history am i a history
enthusiast hell no
i am deadly serious about history
i've been studying history all my life
i'm still studying it
so i am not a history enthusiast i am
deadly serious about history i am not an
expert in history i am a student of
history and i am sharing whatever i'm
learning that's what i'm doing
if you start believing that i'm an
expert in sisters whatever you're never
going to grow past that point point
if you think i know everything now i'm
an expert that's it it's the end of your
growth
so don't ever have that i think that i'm
an expert at something i do not consider
myself an expert at anything i am a
student i'm going to be a lifelong
student i'm going to keep learning and
you know what history is such that
there's always something new to learn
there's so much research happening in
archaeology in
in a whole different
in a whole entire bouquet of sciences
that will give you new information new
insights into history what you thought
was true it may turn out to be false
based on new information new research so
there's always something new to learn
every day every week every month every
year
it's a field that keeps evolving we are
learning so much more about our past
because of scientific advances
so uh you gotta keep learning and you
always need to have a open mind like
i've shared my my story about how i used
to believe in the arena and vision
method
based on my actual study of the actual
evidence the entire
perspective was changed and i was
i was fine with that
i my entire understanding and
perspective of our history took a
complete 360 degree 180 degree turn and
that did not uh create any cognitive
dishones or anything or anything in me
so uh so i'm a learner
i'm not an enthusiast i'm not not an
expert i'm learning and i'm sharing
whatever i learn is it possible to get
mastery in a subject
by just by self-study without getting a
degree let's say you're learning pottery
how to make pots
do you get degrees in pottery no
you learn how to make great pots to do
to become an expert at pottery by
practicing every single day hours every
day that's how you gain mastery in it
there is no degree in pottery similarly
whether it comes to any subject any
field whether it's economics or physics
or mathematics or history you can get a
significant amount of proficiency
without ever whether without ever uh
trying to earn a degree
so it is possible to get gain mastery in
a subject
through pure self-study nothing else i
mean
whatever i've learned is through
self-study i have gone to school college
university etc i have degrees in
whatever
i did not learn a single thing ever in
the classroom whatever i learned was
through self-study after i left
classroom went back home and i spent a
few hours studying things on my own from
whatever books i found valuable and
useful
so everything i've learned in any field
has been through self-study those
degrees whatever i have they they
actually gave me just a paper a degree
that's it nothing else so that's what i
would say to all of you
uh self-study is the best way to study i
mean depending on the person for me
that's the way it works for some people
you may need a teacher to teach you so
it depends on you you what your aptitude
is what kind of person you are but for
me self-study is what has always worked
anime says ever since i have started
listening to your thoughts my entire
identity has been shaken on one hand
i've become immensely confident and the
strong nationalist which is great and i
love it but on the other hand it has
made me skeptical about everything i
consume for knowledge
this is causing a great deal of
turbulence and i no longer
i'm no longer able to enjoy the things i
used to before whether it's watching
movies or reading books or news that
belong to the west i know i should find
balance i'm feeling biased
is this a phase that will pass
as i gather more knowledge any
recommendations you know life is a com
is a learning experience and the truth
is that the media
has been telling you what to think
it's not like it's something that's
happened in the past five or ten years
the media has always been lying to you
the media has always been owned by
somebody or the other
every see the
news is an industry industry means there
is money in it it's it's a money-making
industry so there are people who own
news organizations when somebody owns a
news organization they're going to make
sure that the news that comes out of
that organization has
a certain bias that reflects their world
view and their ideology and their
perspectives it's always going to be
that way and media is so powerful that
governments control it surreptitiously
like the bbc is the propaganda arm of
the uk government
cnn
new york times new york washington post
etc are the propaganda arms
of the
us government and so on and so forth the
thing is we don't have any propaganda we
are not able to promote our propaganda
why why should we not so we don't have
that but you know when this curtain that
you that was over your eyes is removed
then it kind of shakes you up the first
time it happens it's like if you see if
you see the movie the matrix it's like
you take the red pill and then you see
the real world in all its ugliness but
it is the truth
so i would say that yeah it's uh it can
cause some turbulence when everything
you've believed all these years
is now revealed to be false you've taken
the red pill you know like they say
and
now you see the world and it's not as
pretty as you thought or imagined it was
that's a passing phase eventually you
get used to it and you know i
i would take the truth 100 times out of
100 over beautiful lies
and yeah even i used to enjoy watching
certain movies that i kind of don't
enjoy anymore
i used to enjoy watching certain
sometimes some bollywood movies i don't
want to watch them anymore because now i
know the truth about bollywood and the
kind of propaganda they are spewing and
the kind of uh
distortions about india they are
constantly engaging in for decades so
that's one example the all the news that
comes from the west is
you simply can't trust it all the books
that are authored by western authors you
have to be very careful about what you
believe when you read the books you
should read the books
but you should always
take everything with a few grains of
salt so that's how it is so i went
through that
i've been going through that for the
past 20 or so years
uh i'm glad you're going through it it
will cause some turbulence be equanimous
be calm and
always search for the truth so it's a
passing phase you will get used to it
well my recommendations are consume as
much knowledge as you can
from all possible sources and then use
your judgment to understand what is
right and what is actually propaganda
it's it's a skill that evolves over time
it's a skill that you acquire and refine
over time so give it time it will happen
harsh says your views on atlantic city
is it real or not
it's real
i i've been there
i was in atlantic city
it's 22 now right i was in atlantic city
about two decades ago the first time
it's very much real and i remember
visiting the trump taj mahal casino
because i wanted to see what a casino
looks like so atlantic city is indeed
real i have been there personally it's
not a myth atlantis
is something we still don't know about
so there is this uh
old greek story of this city called
atlantis that supposedly sank in the
ocean
and uh
it disappeared because of a tectonic
event earthquake or something
so there they were the western countries
have been the western world has been
looking for the city of atlantis for for
centuries they even named an entire
ocean after the city the atlantic ocean
but they have never found atlantis there
there's only one city i can think of a
major city prosperous city very
well-governed city
that
was destroyed overnight in a couple of
hours in a massive tectonic event an
earthquake that is the city of burka
and it was considered to be a myth by
indian historians for decades
until unfortunately they actually found
the ruins of the city exactly where the
so-called myth said it would be so the
only city that matches the description
of the greek atlantis is the indian city
of dwarka which is like maybe eight ten
thousand years old maybe even older it's
a massive big city with big walls and
all that it's there under the ocean
it's still there hopefully they're not
destroying it so
so that's about atlantis and also about
atlantic city these are two different
things
okay karthik says can you please tell us
about the law of casualty
i think you mean causality
so what is causality its cause and
effect
from the time of the big bang
everything that has happened after the
big bang has been connected to the
initial moments after the big bang
through
well mathematics differential equations
the entire universe can be governed
you can
if you if you know all the parameters
you could represent it by a single wave
function a single differential equation
so cause and effect every effect has a
certain cause that causes it
the world we live in today
it is the result of decisions taken by
our predecessors our ancestors
centuries ago even thousands of years
ago
if a bunch of people 70 000 or so years
ago did not decide to cross the bab
al-mandeb strait
which is today called the babel month of
straight in the red sea and cross out of
africa into asia then we would not be
alive here today
so for every effect there is a cause
it's a causal chain cause and effect
cause an effect cause an effect that's
that's the law of causality
right and the study of history is the
study of cause and effect causality the
causal chain and that's what people
don't teach you your teachers will not
teach you that because they themselves
don't understand that your textbooks
will not tell you that the study of
history is that study of cause and
effect causality but it's not a law as
such it's just the
understanding that for everything that
happens there is a cause for it if you
can identify the cause then you can
understand why things happen and you can
actually start predicting what may
happen in the future to a reasonable
amount of accuracy so that is causality
and you know
there is there are applications for this
in geopolitics in in business in finance
and economics and many other fields
predictive analytics
so it's possible today because of
uh super computers of data mining all of
that you can feed a massive amount of
data into a machine learning algorithm
into a neural network and that neural
network is going to make predictions for
you based on how you train it and how uh
how
all encompassing and broad and unbiased
your data set is and so on so that again
is
on the on the basis of causality cause
and effect
so that is
what causality is the cause and effect
chain
asmita says it's great to be part of
this amazing journey thank you thank you
smitha here's my question how should a
read leader respond to criticism many
dictators are despised for their brutal
ways of dealing with it
there are also many leaders who are
perceived as weak
for not having a response or a meek one
what is the best way of dealing with
criticism for a leader
uh please also answer this one more tiny
question have you given a thought about
writing science fiction okay let's talk
about leadership and criticism how
should a leader respond to criticism it
depends on the leader a good leader will
put the national let's talk about
national leaders we can talk about all
kinds of leaders even if you are
a member of a family you are in a way a
leader you can assume a leadership role
in a small five-person family or even a
three-person family so leadership
exists at multiple levels now let's talk
about a higher level just to make things
clear it applies everywhere so let's
talk about nations and national leaders
so if you are a leader of a nation
hopefully
the
highest
objective for you as a national leader
is to pursue and further and protect and
promote your national interest
that should be the only objective of a
leader nothing else
your entire existence should revolve
around
promoting furthering protecting the
national interest the long-term national
interest right
that is the
in the concise definition of leadership
and national interest so if you are a
leader and
your the the only objective you
serve
or follow
is to promote the national interest and
then if somebody criticizes you then the
only question you have to ask yourself
as a leader is is this criticism valid
am i doing something wrong am i harming
my nation's interest so you should take
criticism seriously as a leader and you
should analyze it properly and if it is
valid you should do some kind of course
correction based on what insight you
have acquired from the criticism
but unfortunately there are many
so-called leaders who
don't
uh
value the nation's interest look at
what's happening in sri lanka
there's a family that that's running the
country and they they are right now busy
trying to save their skin and try to
stay in power the country be damned so
there are there are leaders like that
those are not real leaders
a leader
is someone who serves the country when
you have a person in a so-called
leadership position but they are serving
their own family they are not real
leaders so you cannot consider such
people to be leaders i'm just giving an
example there are lots of other examples
like that
uh i'm sure you can think of many of
those
so
a a genuine leader a true leader will
take criticism very seriously
and introspect based on the criticism
first analyze whether the criticism is
valid it is genuine
or not if the criticism is valid then
they have to understand where they are
going wrong based on the feedback they
have received and they should make the
appropriate course correction so that is
the correct way for a leader to respond
to criticism don't take it personally
the nation
is is above the leader
the leader is merely a servant so if the
service there is something wrong with
the service they need to do course
correction even if it proves that they
were doing something wrong so be it
serve the nation forget about how you
look
so that is how a true leader would
should respond to criticism have i given
thought to writing science fiction
not really i am a big fan of science
fiction i have never thought about
writing fiction i mean
once or twice i may have written some
little
short story or something obviously never
published but yeah nothing never
seriously thought about writing fiction
or science fiction
maybe someday when i have a lot of time
in the future distant future i may think
of doing that
maybe not yet maybe not yet
okay himalayan anka says i am currently
reading your recommended book kudeta by
edward luthor which mentions one of the
preconditions for coup is economic
backwardness whereas you and dr luthwak
in your podcast said a coup is possible
in china which is a country with the
second highest gdp so how is a coup
possible in china then please explain
excellent question i love it
so yes uh that's what the book mentions
that one of the
preconditions
for a coup is economic backwardness and
i had this discussion with dr lutwak in
my podcast it's available for you to
watch brilliant podcast brilliant
conversation brilliant guest so so we
discussed the possibility of a coup
in china and he went into some detail or
detail about how
aku would be
a hypothetical coup in china would take
place so yes he did agree that a coup is
possible in china but not in india
right so one of the conditions is
economic backwardness now you're saying
that uh and you're rightly saying china
is the country with the second highest
gdp in the world so
how is a coup possible then because one
of the conditions is economic
backwardness well
we're talking about the condition of the
people not the condition of the country
china has a population of 1.4 billion
people if you take the overall gdp
per
the annual gdp you divide it by the
number of people then you then you get
the per capita gdp it's not very high
it's not very high
right
so you can have a gdp of a bazillion
dollars but if your population is a
gazillion
then bazillion divided by gazillion is
the actual uh
indicator of economic progress or
backwardness if your per capita gdp is
like 2 000 per year that's economic
backwardness in the case of china it's
no longer that much it's around 10 000
or so
roughly give or take so it's not
entirely economic backward but it's not
economically uh
prosperous
the people are not prosperous yet and we
don't know uh
the actual conditions inside china
because even if you
do this calculation of per capita gdp
you failed to take into account the
possible inequality in society for
instance in a country like china which
is a dictatorship a one-party
dictatorship there will be a significant
amount of economic inequality a small
percent of the population will hold
most of the money of the country or
wealth of the country
so
let's let's take the case of the us
in the u.s approximately two percent of
the population has more has
more than 60 70 percent or so of the
entire country's wealth
these oligarchs
they call them billionaires in the us
when it's another in another country
they call them oligarchs
so these american oligarchs they
hold
they are in possession of the majority
of the countries well there is this
massive inequality wealth inequality in
the us
and there are many people who survive
by doing two three jobs a day they sleep
four hours a day and the rest of the
time they're working just to put food on
the table for the families so i expect
in china the situation may be similar or
even worse because the chinese have
tried to copy the american model
of capitalism
so because of these facts and you know
in china these things are hidden
what you see in the media is the nice
nice version of china what they want you
to believe
they don't show you what they don't want
you to see there's so much about china
that is hidden you only see the official
version on twitter or whatever whatever
their social media accounts are and it's
it's strange that twitter allows the
chinese to to
to
pass on this misinformation at an
industrial scale
right so what you see about china is not
necessarily the truth about china
they are showing china as a beautiful
heavenly nation full of forests and
orchids orchards and and
glimmer glimmering glittering cities and
wealth and all that there's a whole
different part of china that they're not
showing you
right
so there that's the reason why a coup is
very much possible in china
the communist party is politburo and the
the top leadership will hold much of the
country's wealth
there are many billionaires in china but
you know every two or three weeks a
billionaire disappears in china for
whatever reason
so there's a whole
lot that is swept under the carpet and
hidden away from you there are lots of
systemic and other problems in china
and that is the reason why
despite the high gdp of the country and
despite the reasonably okay per capita
gdp the truths may be something very
different and most likely is very
different there is a great deal of
poverty even now in china they claim
they have eliminated extreme poverty and
all that
they also claim that there was no kovid
in china for two years
yeah do you believe that
so don't trust everything
that you see
so that's why a coup is very much
possible in china and there are two
other conditions as well which i'm sure
you have read about if you all don't
know about it check out the book there
are three preconditions for a coup and
in china all three are satisfied and
that's why it's a country that is
that is
likely to have a coup in the future at
least you know as long as the communist
party is in power
okay
rtk says you put low you put a lot of
load on your brain by doing multiple
heavy tasks does it impact your mental
health do you take a break from all of
this or is it something about mental
fitness or toughness if it is so would
you like to give some tips about mental
fitness
i don't put heavy loads on my brain
i don't do multiple heavy tasks
i know the limitations of this brain
my i have a small
moderate brain it can't do heavy tasks
it simply cannot do multiple tasks i
this my brain is incapable of
multitasking i only do one thing at a
time
that's what i do
so uh
i never over tax or overload my brain
i mean there is this myth
in the corporate world about
multitasking a good manager or a good
leader in the corporate world is
somebody who can do five things at the
same time that's a myth simply can't be
done
if somebody does it well good on them i
can't do it
so so
i am very clear about where i am my
brain can't do such things i can only do
focus on one thing at a time so that's
how i do things
uh so yeah that's that's how i've always
been i've never had any mental health
issues i'm not saying when mental health
issues don't exist these days among the
newer generations among
gen z etc there is this there seems to
be this epidemic of mental health issues
and all that
which is unfortunate
and it's almost like if you don't have
mental health issues then you're
abnormal that's how it's become
because of the media and whatever so
everybody
i don't know lots of people lots of kids
seem to have mental health issues
depression or whatever it is which is
unfortunate me i have never had any
mental health issues
maybe maybe i'm lucky or whatever
so yeah
whatever i do it does not ever impact my
mental health do i take a break from
things sometimes i do i sometimes i you
know in every single
day um
but you have 24 hours in a day maybe you
sleep eight hours a day which and you're
left with 16
so you're gonna spend some time maybe
seven eight hours or whatever works for
you doing whatever work you're doing
whatever is important to you the work
serious part which you have to focus on
but you also have to take some time out
in the day maybe three four hours or
whatever works for you when you're doing
nothing you are supposedly wasting time
because the brain needs that too
doing activities in which you know not
creating anything not not producing
anything
hanging out with friends
watching a movie
or playing music or going to the gym or
swimming or whatever or be with your
family
doing things that are supposedly
non-productive but the mind needs that
that keeps the balance in the mind so
for some people you may need four hours
of that some people may need one hour of
that
so it depends on everybody so you need
to have a balanced life
don't skimp out on sleep that will mess
up your mind for sure
so that's what i can say that's the tips
i would say i would give about mental
fitness keep things simple don't try to
achieve 15 different things at the same
time
so that's how we should do things uh
take breaks yes you should take breaks
you should have a certain time in every
single day when you're doing nothing or
doing something that you enjoy listening
to music watching movies hanging out
with friends whatever it is so i have
certain things that i like once in a
while i like to go out and travel
somewhere get in get on an airplane go
somewhere i enjoy traveling so that's
something i like to do once in a while
that's again starting now because this
the past two years are behind us now so
you know you should always take a break
once in a while there should be a daily
break and maybe a monthly or quarterly
break or whatever so
you should not always be in the same
routine because routine kind of
dulls the mind
do things that are different from time
to time so that's what i would say and
don't take life too seriously sometimes
things don't work out sometimes things
don't work out for a long time hey
that's life
stuff happens
just move on
um
akash says generally speaking the
followers of sanatana are more tolerant
compared to
religious faiths even in india there are
where there's a majority of uh sanatanas
in even for the namesake
there are hardly any approach against
selective criticism and abuse of vedic
literature on social media targeting our
festivals even our dear their name
leela etc
if somebody makes fun of guru granth
sahib or quran even in foreign countries
they'll be punished probably killed no
such anger is seen in us the my question
is does it serve us or is it going
against us in the current times
well there is something that uh
that hindus need to think about uh
i obviously am against any form of
violence
so
the thing is in india there is a
selective application of laws india
unfortunately is the most hindu phobic
country in the world i say this without
a hint of irony it is true the
constitution is is foreign in nature
there are clauses in the constitution
that are unequal that target
hinduism adversely the policies of the
government are a hindu phobic anti-hindu
whether it's education policy whether it
is the the hijacking of hindu temples
and stealing of the wealth and so on so
forth
so first of all hindu should realize
that india is the most hindu phobic
country in the world
hindus are treated like second class or
third-class citizens hindus have more
equal equality
in western countries than in india
you have the same rights as a hindu as
in other countries like in the us or in
europe
as people of other religions in india
you don't
so india is the most hindu phobic
country in the world now uh
most people don't care in india because
over the past few decades the education
system is completely about deracinated
people so they feel no connection to
their to their culture as religious
roots so they don't care if people abuse
hinduism and so on so what i would say
is
this if it continues it's going to end
up
destroying in those hinduism will no
longer exist in 50 or 100 years you know
it will be a very minor
fringe
faith
so that's eventually what will happen if
the country continues on its current
path so i obviously would say that i am
totally against any form of
violence
uh whatever punishments
should be given have to be done have to
be given as per the law now the law
itself is unequal so you know things
need to change
i am not asking for hinduism to become
the supremacist religion in the country
or the primary religion in the country
every religion every
faith every culture
that is inside india should have a level
playing field that's all i'm saying
so uh yeah the way things are going
hinduism will go extinct in 5200 years
more or less it will become irrelevant
in the fringe thing the way things are
currently going so hopefully you should
be aware of this and
and
hopefully
things should change
how does it how do things change it will
change
because of the right leadership if we
get the right leadership i'm not saying
i'm not saying we have the wrong
leadership right now
right now things are such that certain
things cannot be done
eventually in the future we will have
equality in the country and every
citizen will have the same rights which
they don't have today so i am not asking
for more rights for group x or group y i
am saying everybody should have the same
rights i think nobody should be should
ever have any objection to that
it says is it correct that the mughals
or the persians are not actually the
founders of biryani
according to some articles sanskrit text
like
park
mentions that anisha the king in nala
who when he left his own kingdom and
became a cook in ayodhya king
rituparna's kitchen was the fun was the
one who invented what we now call
biryani what is the truth okay
so if you study your history textbooks
if you listen to your eminent historians
if you watch
if you listen to
if you consume media
and all that
what you will be told is that biryani is
one of the great gifts that the turks
they're called mughals right in our
textbooks but they're turks
so the turks gave india a great gift
this wonderful flavorful dish called
biryani it is a meat dish but you hindus
eat it in a vegetarian way but still you
should thank the mughals the turks for
that that's what they're telling
that's what the you are taught and most
of us believe that right
so
simple question
where did the turks come from the
so-called mughals where did they come
from
they came
from central asia would you like to see
what central asia is
let me show you
because
the map will help to understand
so this here is india i know you could
recognize india so this entire place if
you can see my mouse pointer i'm hoping
that you can see it
so this is central asia north of the
himalayas
all of this is central asia kazakhstan
and so on so forth all of that is
central asia
uh east of the
essence north and east of the caspian
sea that is central asia
so the turks came from this overall
region they were also present for the
north in siberia and so on so the turks
who are now known as the mughals they
came from that region
central asia now simple question
biryani what is the major ingredient in
biryani
it's rice
does rice grow in central asia
answer me that question
you don't know it
google it
find out for yourself homework
does rice grow in central asia
let me give you the answer rice doesn't
grow anywhere in central asia there is
no rice cultivation anywhere in central
asia
so if rice
does not grow in central asia if there
is no rice cultivation in central asia
how did a rice dish became
the dish of the turks how did they
invent a dish
based on a staple food that doesn't even
grow there
where does rice grow
rice grows in places where there's a lot
of water lots of rainfall india
and parts of china in parts of southeast
asia etc
that's where rice is a staple crop in a
staple food grain
right
so how can biryani
be a central asian dish or turkey dish
they lived there for thousands of years
without any rice
even if they would get rice from
somewhere else possibly it would be
something like a luxury for them that
simply cannot become a national dish
of the turks
and about persia well even in persia
rice doesn't grow there
the favorite rice
of the persian people of our persian
brethren in cistern
is
long grain basmati rice they import it
from india
maybe some of it from pakistan or
whatever
so the persians love rice
they get it from india they love basmati
so if you look at these simple facts it
becomes very clear that that biryani or
pulav or whatever rice dish cannot any
of these rice dishes none of these rice
dishes could have emerged out of central
asia simply because rice doesn't grow
there
so
that itself totally invalidates the
argument that these
invaders
they enriched us culturally by bringing
in this rice dish
we enrich them culturally
they acquired these dishes
these flavors these spices everything
from us
right so i'm not aware of these
whatever
these
points that you've mentioned the
sanskrit text and nisha the king and
allah and
all that i'm not aware of that but it's
simple logic that biryani could not have
emerged out of central asia it's an
indian dish and of course
there must be lots of evidence from old
cook books etc
about various rice dishes
that existed in ancient india obviously
they would have existed there is
evidence of rice cultivation that goes
back 10 000 years before today in india
so rice has always been part of india so
obviously indians 10 000 years ago would
have been eating rice dishes
cuisine has always been part of our life
so that should set the matter to rest
these lies need to be exposed our
historians our so-called eminent
historians have been lying to all of you
and all of us
they are liars
exposed debunked
okay radio says are all indian
did all indian dinosaurs go extinct
during the formation of the deccan traps
or did they go extinct because of the
events caused by the chikulub event okay
what is the context to what
the question is so let's go back to the
map where's the map shall we make it
larger here we are
so
the question is about the deccan traps
and the chichalub event
so as
i hope we all know
the indian subcontinent
the indian land mass was once part of
africa
it was once attached to africa the
eastern part of africa
right
so it detached because of uh tectonic
activity about 100 million or so years
before today
the island of madagascar also detached
it
it was left behind here and the indian
land mass
traveled all across the indian ocean and
eventually slammed into eurasia and that
is the event that led to the formation
of the highest mountain the tallest
mountain range in the world the
himalayas
so
when india was in the indian ocean when
the indian subcontinent
was in the indian ocean
when it was in this region here
the union island region
about 60 70 million years before today
about 65 or so millionaires before today
the indian subcontinent was in this
region
the reigning region and there is a
volcanic hot spot there it's called the
reunion hotspot
so at that time there was this massive
super volcanic activity going on in
the deccan planes in the deccan plateau
and you still see evidence of that
in the deccan plateau it's called the
dick traps these bad lands in
maharashtra and
western india even central india and all
that enormous
region
that was full of this super volcanism
and this super volcanism this super
volcanic activity spewed immense amounts
of
fumes smoke dust
clouds ash etc into the earth's
atmosphere
this happened about
between 70 and 60 million years before
today approximately 67 66 65 million
years before today
so that is a deccan traps volcanism
and at the same time
there was this massive extraterrestrial
impact
onto the earth
so if we go to mexico's yucatan
province yucatan peninsula
and if you go to this region here you
will find a town called chikshalub
it's not a town it's a village
chikshalub this is the place
so it's a small village today chikshalub
and it happens to be the epicenter
of an ancient
uh extraterrestrial impact event that
happened 66 million years ago
so if you go to
go to google
and you
google it
google this and if you take a look at
the
the images here once again
so you will find evidence
of an ancient hidden crater
in this region
as you can see
there are all these sinkholes called
cenotes
that are laid out in a ring
with its epicenter near the city the the
village of chichalub
so and there are these gravitational
anomalies as well and all of that so
it's clear that there is an ancient
massive
impact crater hidden
in the
uh
yucatan peninsula and this impact it has
been dated to around 66 million years
ago before today and we know what
happened at the time the extinction
event of the non-avian dinosaurs it was
a massive extinction event so what
happened is that there was a massive
space object
maybe an asteroid or a comet
that impacted the earth in that place in
present-day yucatan
this object was about 10 kilometers in
diameter it was traveling at
approximately 20 to 30 kilometers per
second
and the kinetic energy of the impact was
about roughly
billion
5 billion times
is it 5 million i think it's 5 million
times 5 million times the energy of the
hiroshima atomic bomb
that's 50 lakh times
the energy
emitted by the hirohima nuclear bomb
that was the energy released by this
enormous extraterrestrial impact so it
clearly caused a global catastrophe it
caused a nuclear kind of winter
it spewed enormous amounts of ash and
dust and soil and smoke and salt and all
that into the atmosphere which remained
in earth's atmosphere for maybe a decade
so maybe for a decade or so
there was no sunlight
that killed off most of the plants
and when all the plants die the animals
that eat plants the herbivorous animals
die and when herbivorous animals die the
animals that eat those herbivorous
animals they also die so that set of
mass extinction event maybe 90 95 of all
species on the planet died out
including the non-avian dinosaurs
but some tiny animals
survived including the avian dinosaurs
who eventually evolved into into today's
birds
and also some small mammals survived rat
like animals
who gave rise to us
so our ancestors survived that
now the question is
what caused the mass extinction
of the dinosaurs it is not only indian
dinosaurs that died it's the global
dinosaur population non-avian dinosaurs
that died out so the big controversy has
been
what caused
this mass extinction was it the lobe
impact event which was a massive event
or was it the deccan traps volcanism in
india
so there's been a massive controversy
there is this lady who came up with this
idea that the theory that it was the
deccan traps volcanism
that caused this uh impact this mass
extinction
and
she was marginalized and laughed off for
decades i think i've even written about
this
where do we have it i let me share the
screen
so i have actually written about this
so this is an article i wrote in 2018
so
the mainstream consensus is nobel
laureate luis alvarez's famous bad
weekend scenario big rock from the sky
hits the dinosaurs and boom they go the
day out and the discovery of the 66
million year old chichalub glitter
crater has bolstered this theory's
credibility
but one geologist disagrees and she has
endured decades of ridicule for it
girtha keller argues that the cretaceous
paleogene extinction event the dinosaur
extinction was caused by a series of
colossal volcanic eruptions they dictant
traps in india and their environmental
consequences
and this lady had to endure decades of
ridicule and all that
but now it is widely accepted that it
was most likely a combination
of the chichalub event
and the deccan traps volcanism a
combination of these two things these
two factors that caused the extinction
event of the dinosaurs and other animals
right so most likely it is a combination
of two factors the massive volcanism
supervolcanism in india the deccan traps
and at the same time the chicholu
impact event both of these
had consequences that eventually got
together and caused the
extinction event
66 million years ago the cretaceous
paleogene extinction event so most
likely it's a combination of both the
factors
okay hedgehogs dilemma says what is the
true history of slavery in india
european
scholars say that dasa refers to slave
so europeans are going to teach us what
the meaning of sanskrit words
are
you know it's
it's
i think the whole world agrees that it
is wrong to study
jewish culture
based on what the nazis wrote about the
jews
it's also dishonest to form an opinion
about
china
based on what the west writes about
china you have to read chinese
scholarship to understand what china is
right
but it's somehow perfectly fine to base
your entire research on indian history
based on what the europeans
colonizers wrote about india even today
what the europeans wrote is regarded as
the highest
knowledge and evidence about indian
history and if indians say something
that is
contrary to what the europeans have
written they are ridiculed no no no you
are you indians are stupid so and so
scholar wrote this and that's why it's
right
what evidence do they have that the word
does refers to slave
there is there are multiple sources of
evidence from outside india that attest
to the fact that there was no slavery in
india
right that the word dasa
in sanskrit refers means servant
that's what it means
and das servant i mean even the prime
minister of the country
is the servant of the people in the
servant of the nation is it something
bad to be a servant
no
you don't become a servant by force you
become a servant by choice because you
choose to or because you need to
servitude is not slavery servitude is
voluntary
so the word das
means servant it has a variety of
meanings and contexts in which you can
be a servant you can be a public servant
you can be the servant of a city you can
be the servant of a single family
you can be a servant of a single person
assistant secretary uh whatever
butler
foot
man charioteer
whatever it is right so so the word dasa
means servant if some european comes and
tells you what it means tell them to
move on
that's all i have to say about this
there was never ever any slavery in
india
until the past 1 000 years of india's
humiliation when the turks and then then
the europeans
brought slavery into india
and took indians as slaves before that
there was never ever any slavery in
india
the only evidence they have tried they
have been able to find is the word das
there is no sanskrit word for slave
so they have found the best possible
approximation something that is close to
it and they have tried to portray that
as meaning slave whatever it is they
have for that
do you find slavery in the
archaeological record in india if you go
to rome or wherever the romans ruled you
find archaeological evidence of slavery
you find skeletons who are wearing these
metal bands
skeletons in chains
if you look at the pre-roman history of
of europe you will find slavery there
also evidence of slavery in a variety of
forms you don't find a single a single
uh
instance in the entire 10 000 plus year
archaeological record of india where
there is hard evidence of slavery not
one
so they have tried to create these
distortions through language
entirely false lies fabrications
distortions
and this
is not only the fault of these europeans
even the irfan habibs and the romula
toppers are complicit in this
so they need to be exposed for that
okay har shiado says uh
you said that india is poor because of
colonization then how do you explain the
poverty of nepal which was never
colonized you know this is a good
question
let's understand something
so what is nepal nepal is a nation state
right
first of all
the concept of the nation state
begins in the 17th century with the
treaty of westphalia which happened in
1648 1650 thereabouts look it up if you
want to
the treaty of westphalia is what created
eventually in in the long run the
concept of the westphalian nation state
and the nation-state system that we all
live under today
but for the entirety of human history
we've never had nations we've had
kingdoms
empires and all that that's all we had
so now uh nepal these are facts don't
hate me for it i am just presenting
evidence you can look it up nepal is a
relatively young
nation state
founded solely on the basis of the
conquests of one man prithvi narayan
shah the the founder of nepal so he was
the ruler of the gorkhas in today's
central nepal
and historically nepal this region which
we now call nepal it's been part of
various indian kingdoms and empires it
was part of the mauryan empire it was
part of the kushan empire it was part of
the gupta empire it was part of the the
mughal kingdom and so on and so forth
and so on so forth it's always been
parts of various indian kingdoms and
empires and they're the same people as
us nepalese are not a different
race or anything else same culture same
people same blood same everything
right
so
after this guy this gentleman prithvi
narayan shah captured kathmandu in the
newar valley or nepal valley in the 18th
century mid-18th century roughly
he made it the capital of his kingdom
and his kingdom uh was named after the
nepal nivar valley nepal
so why did nepal
avoid absorption into the british raj
into british india when it was always
part of various indian kingdoms in
empires why was that
it was able to avoid absorption into the
british indian raj
because it was useful as a buffer state
between british india
and the chinese occupied tibet so there
was a time when there was a king dynasty
garrison in tibet
so the british wanted to create a some
safe separation between british india
and in the the
chinese occupied tibet so they used
nepal
as a buffer state and that's why they
kept it autonomous
now just because there was a king
in nepal who was
de facto or or nominally autonomous from
the british doesn't mean that he was
completely autonomous the economy of the
entire subcontinent is inter-related
right
so if you have one kingdom that is not
part of the british raj it doesn't mean
it's completely economically
independent
everything is interrelated it's
interdependent it's an organism
in an economic organism and the
heartland of the indian subcontinent the
wealth of the indian subcontinent has
always been in the river valleys india
is a river valley civilization whereas
the indus valley the saraswati valley
the ganga valley
whatever
it's always been a river valley
civilization that's where the wealth
always lies the navarre valley is high
up in the mountains they what are the
sources of wealth and income there
nothing
why do the people of nepal come to india
to work first of all because we are the
same people we have open borders but
because there is
employment generation wealth
opportunities etc in the the valleys and
the plains of india right
so just because
prithvi narayansha and his successors
were independent nominally doesn't mean
that they they would have been
extremely prosperous nepal is in the
mountains in the hills there's no great
source of wealth over there
and also let's not forget that the
independence of nepal from the british
was only nominal they allowed him to
remain independent it was it was their
choice
but there would have been conditions
let's let's take an example
a painful
example
who fired the bullets in the jalyan
wallabag massacre
i believe there are there was a company
of about 50 soldiers
uh 25 of these soldiers were either
balochis or pashtuns
right
slaves of the british raj
indians who fired upon indians
so 25 of these soldiers were balochis
and pashtuns the other 25 of these
soldiers who fired the bullets in the
jalen walabug massacre were gurkhas
they belonged to the nine gorkha rifles
who were they they were nepalese so if
nepal was so independent
why were gurkhas and nepalese serving in
the british raj and firing upon the upon
their fellow indians
these are facts
right
and if nepal was so prosperous at the
time
why did they have to come and work for
the british raj
so the fact is that
being a hilly mountainous
kingdom nepal never had any great
sources of income
the entire subcontinent was one economic
entity
and when nepal
was prosperous it was because the whole
country was prosperous and when the
british destroyed the country
when british the british
plundered and transferred all the wealth
45 trillion plus dollars of
worth of wealth from india nepal also
suffered the consequences of that
when the whole country was prosperous
even these far-flung hilly regions would
have benefited from the prosperity when
india was destroyed
the far-flung
hilly regions
even they were no even if they were
normally independent also declined
because where's the money
so that is what happened so nepal was
never colonized in i mean officially but
yeah all of these facts are facts the
nepalese were serving in the british raj
as in a variety of capabilities in
capacities right
and even today
there are nepalese gorkhas who go and
serve in the british army
because it's uh well financial benefits
okay diviabari says um
thank you dave i've always wondered
whether it's more important for a
politician or a leader to have a
stronger vision or be extremely clever
especially as you have iis and experts
around you you could say vision and
leadership quality trumps
smartness
also as a leader is it right to excel in
one topic
or have knowledge in
all topics
it doesn't mean you should neglect
intellectuality
listen ias and experts they aren't
leaders they are people who do as they
are told
they they carry out the bureaucratic
activity they don't you cannot consider
them to be leaders
now think about the the great leaders
whom you may admire
uh
historically
or maybe the the
two three leaders of today's two days
world that you admire think about them
what kind of people are there
can you become a great leader
without being extremely clever
it's impossible to think of the great
leaders that you admire today
i can guarantee that whoever you can
think of top three they are all
extremely clear none of them is stupid
or dumb
right
now
on the other hand you may be very clever
but can you become a leader without
having a big
strong long-term vision for your people
in your country
no
a great leader will definitely have a
great vision for the country
some big objective that everybody should
work towards
so the truth is that a leader needs to
have all of these qualities you cannot
become a great leader without having a
great big vision and also being very
very clever very intelligent
and
it's not enough
to have
to excel in just one topic you have to
understand the entire world you have to
understand history geopolitics economics
military matters strategy grant strategy
tactics politics
how to manage people so many things you
understand all of this
so a great leader is somebody a
genuinely great leader would have a good
understanding of all of these topics
it's not about being intellectual
it's about being practical about having
practical knowledge of all of these
things you need to be a genuine
all-rounder in all of these things only
then can you be a genuinely great leader
like a once in a hundred years kind of
leader
you have all these so-called politicians
who call themselves leaders but many of
them are genuine are massively deficient
in many of these these aspects
there are very few
who are good at everything and they are
the ones the ones who are good at all of
these
all of these things they are the ones
who can be considered to be great
leaders and who can make a genuine
positive impact on their country and on
the entire world
so to be a genuinely great leader you
need to be
very clever very intelligent you need to
have a
great vision and you need to have
a very strong understanding of multiple
topics only then can you be a genuinely
great leader
rumble tv says how
what should i do to get respect and
attention in my family they never take
me and my decision seriously
well
think of the people you admire
think of the people you respect
what are they what are their qualities
i can
see there's a difference between liking
somebody and respecting somebody you can
like a person without quite respecting
them there are many people who are very
nice people you know very good people
good hearts
well-meaning people so you like such
people right
but you kind of
you may not quite respect them so what
creates respect
real world achievements create respect
and the greater your achievements
the greater the respect for a person
it's always results real world results
that generate respect for a person in
the eyes of their peers the family or
whoever else society
so the more you achieve
the more you
offer to society or the more you gain
for yourself the more you'll be
respected and the more you offer society
the more respect you'll have so how do
you gain respect and attention in your
family firstly produce produce some
real-world results the simplest form of
achieve of producing real-world results
is to get a job and earn money
the moment you become financially
independent
you will gain a certain amount of
respect in a family you will not be
disrespected anymore
you are financially independent you're
not dependent on other people for money
that itself brings you a certain amount
of respect
now if you are earning 30 000 a month
and you're financially independent it's
okay
at least you will gain respect that this
person is independent
but if you are able to
increase your earnings to let's say five
lakh rupees a month
well that's going to
increase the magnitude of respect that's
how the world works unfortunately
people are very shallow very superficial
if you are earning a lot you you will
automatically gain respect
so that's what it is
but real respect
on a large scale you will get if you
contribute something genuinely valuable
to society as a whole
so that's that's bigger respect you know
in the long term respect so if you're
talking about your family the first
thing is become financially independent
produce
some real world results and you will
immediately gain respect in your family
and then you will not have to worry
about whether they take your decision
seriously or not you would be able to
make decisions independently and that
itself is more than enough for a person
to start off with
so
that's the advice i can offer
aman raj says what should we do after
repeated failures even after working
hard it actually hurts
yes it does it hurts
well i don't know what you're working
towards i don't know the specifics so i
can offer you general advice you have
two options
either change your
objectives that's option a change your
objectives change your goals
or option b is change your strategy
so maybe
whatever you're trying to achieve and
you're failing maybe it's not the right
target for you or not not the right goal
for you maybe you're going in the wrong
direction maybe you should be taking
your life in a different direction you
should have a different objective there
is one possibility so recalibrate your
goals that is one thing you could
look into
otherwise if the objectives you're
trying to achieve are indeed the correct
objectives for your life
then you need to change your strategy
what is a strategy
it's a map
a map of how to get from point a to
point b
without a map you simply cannot cross
the road or traverse the distance
you need a map
of how to get from point a to point b
that is your strategy
as long as you have a map you will get
there
if your map is bad then it will take you
years to get there or maybe you won't
get there but if you have a good map you
will get there quickly and you will make
significant progress so your map is your
strategy you need to know how to get to
where you want to get
so how do you change your map how do you
get the right map by studying the world
how did other people achieve what i am
trying to achieve study their successes
study how they achieved it
so that's the general advice i can give
yeah it hurts but if you're failing
repeatedly something is wrong either you
got the wrong goals or you are using the
wrong map
change one or both
if you change one
you may see results if you change both
again you may see results so you need to
decide what is best what is the right
approach for you whether you want to
change your goals or change your
strategy all the best sir
nikhil swami says what if the british or
any european forces did not invade india
and the sultanate had ruled all the way
until the present
how might have the demography of india
look like
this is something i would have believed
20 years ago
you know if you
some 20 years ago i had a different view
of the world i thought the british did a
very good thing for india they saved us
from the turks they freed india they
gave us education they gave us the
english language they gave us
railways blah blah blah blah blah that's
what i used to believe 20 25 years ago
then my eyes were opened and i learned
studied actual history the truth is
the british did not destroy the
sultanate
the british destroyed the maratha empire
the marathas had destroyed annihilated
the turkic
sultanate and there's a map which we can
look at
high tide
of the maratha empire
let's take a look at that let me share
my screen
so this is the maratha empire from
the mid-18th century
as you can see they had wiped out the
so-called delhi sultanate and reclaimed
large portions of india
and liberated large portions of india
so this was the high tide of the maratha
empire 1759 where is the delhi sultanate
it's nowhere to be seen
unfortunately the marathas could not
well
they had all this infighting they they
they had this
well a number of issues
because of which and the british and the
british were able to take advantage of
that and slowly gradually take over
india so the british and the europeans
did not
liberate india from the sultanate it was
the marathas who liberated india and
established what they called hinduism
the british destroyed that
so that's what the british did and they
did so many
terrible things in india which i have
gone into in the past so
had the british
not invaded in india and not destroyed
the maratha empire the demography of
india would have looked starkly
different very different india would
have been what people like to call today
what hindu rashtra that's what india
would have been and the national
language of india would have been
marathi these are obviously
that's that's just logic right
so that's what would have happened
says
were the french more sympathetic towards
the natives when they occupied
territories what would india have looked
like if it was a french instead of the
british ruled during the 19th and 20th
century the french had the same
objective that the british as a british
the french were just as brutal as the
british the french also destroyed
temples and built churches over them go
to south india go to pondicherry guru
tamil nadu you will feel you'll find
lots of examples where the french ruled
and the destroyed temples and built
churches over them these are facts
these are facts whether people like it
or not come on facts of facts facts
don't care about anyone's feelings
the french would have been just as
brutal they would have done the very
same things the british did but the only
difference is that we would be speaking
french today
all of us would be speaking in french
and we would be thinking that french is
the greatest language in the world hindi
sanskrit gujarati tamil etc is poor
french
vive la france
so that's the only difference we would
have seen they would still be completely
mentally colonized the way we are today
that's the only difference
okay neil mehta says once you mentioned
about your interest in chess so what's
your opinion or gary kasparov as a
player and his views about vladimir
putin about his about how he is an evil
dictator
yes a chess is a game that i used to
really enjoy a kid then i gave it up
because it's very time consuming you
play a chess game you'll spend 2-3 hours
playing it if you're serious you know
so i was good i was reasonably good at
it but i never played professionally or
anything i used to enjoy it as a kid
but then i quit the game too time
consuming uh gary kasparov great player
one of the greatest of all time
very interesting history he was from
azerbaijan in the ussr it's presently an
independent country
so uh gary kasparov was born gary
weinstein i think weinstein
his actual surname was weinstein his
father his father was a jew
so he is half jewish his mother was
armenian i think
and
because the ussr was kind of
anti-semitic or whatever that's why he
took up his mother's side surname and
became kasparov or something so that's
his background he was always a very good
player chess player as a kid
he became world champion i think in 1984
by this
by defeating
anatoly karpov his compatriot russian
compatriot
they had two a world championship
matches the first one went like it was a
massive champion championship match
30 40 chess matches they played
karpov was leading 5-0 then kasparov
changed his entire strategy
and then he started started slowly
clawing his way back
the
game the score became five three or five
four or something and then it was so
exhausting more than 40 games had been
played so the championship was called
off think about these chess games chess
is a cerebral sport but if you partici
if a professional chess player a
grandmaster participates in a week long
week-long tournament they're gonna end
up losing four or five or maybe 10 kilos
of weight that's how much mental energy
the game takes
and the brain is the most energy hungry
organ in the body
so chess players if they participate in
extended tournaments they may end up
losing five or ten kilos of weight
that's how
intense this game is so these guys
kasparov and karpov they played more
than 40 games i think in the first
championship and then it had to be
abandoned because it would have killed
them both they both wanted to continue i
believe but then it was abandoned then
the same year a few months later there
was a rematch
and that i think kasparov won and he
became world champion at the age of i
don't know
it was an 84 i think i don't know what
his age was he was very young
and then he was
he went on to become one of the greatest
champions of all time he defeated
various other people including uh
nigel short
vicious
eventually i think he lost to vladimir
kramnik
and he retired in the 2000s i believe he
also lost to a machine the first
human grandmaster or champion to lose to
a machine deep blue i think it was
called
a chess machine just computer so that's
about him as a player one of the
greatest players of all time he was a
very intense player when he would have
made his move and the other player was
he was waiting for the other player to
make make his move or her move mostly
his move he would constantly stare at
the person stare stare still glare into
their eyes to
put this mental pressure on the person
so he had these tactics he would use and
he i think he was fond of staying
physically strong and fit which is
important for a chess player so one of
the greatest of all times no doubt about
that
after retirement he's become very
politically active i think he's
he has formed a political party or he's
a member of a political party something
like that it's a pro-west political
party anti-putin political party so his
views are very strong about putin he
considers putin to be an evil dictator
he believes
kasparov believes in democracy western
democracy liberal democracy whatever he
is very strongly anti-putin pro-west and
so on so forth so
that's about him and his politics
so
the thing is you can admire somebody
without agreeing with their politics
like i've said before there are many
people i admire as human beings for
their achievements in their whatever
field it is but you don't have to agree
with their politics so i admire kasparov
for his achievements in chess one of the
greatest chess players of all time one
of the greatest
sports people of all time
but i don't quite agree with his
politics but and he has the right to
what have whatever he views he has and
that's fine
so that's
my view about
gary kasparov
uh
pronomo anindo says my heart okay thank
you so much my question is
scientists have taken a photograph of a
black hole recently
but even
but if even light cannot escape the
gravitational pull of the black hole
how was the picture taken anyway since
it would require light
isn't it is there something more to it
let us go to that
so there was this picture that was taken
let me share that on the screen
so this is the picture taken by the
event horizon telescope it's this fuzzy
image
of a black hole
this is a simulation of what
it should have looked like and this is
the actual image so what are we seeing
in this we are seeing
a
reasonably circular
ring of light
and a dark portion
the dark portion is the actual black
hole the edge of the dark portion
is the event horizon the point of no
return
and all of this luminous material is the
accretion disk
so it's the what we are seeing is the
light from the accretion disk
we are not actually seeing the black
hole which is dark
right
so we are seeing the effect the black
hole has on its surroundings
which is the accretion disk which is all
of this material that is falling into
the black hole and it is falling at
supersonic velocities it's heating up
and it's emitting enormous amounts of
light so that is what we are seeing
and the actual black hole is the dark
portion so we don't see it there is no
light there
so
so the picture is of the light
and the material that surrounds the
black hole in the dark portion is the
actual black hole so it's a picture not
of the black hole itself but the light
and the effect that it has around it
so so that is correct
we can't actually see darkness
so the darkness is the dark portion
so
that's correct right
so what we are seeing is not the black
hole itself but its effect on the
surroundings and we can see the shape of
the black hole the dark shape which is
spherical
so there is nothing more to it it's very
simple
okay they just says how would you advise
youngsters like me to manage their
personal finance how much amount of your
monthly income should you save
the answer is simple save as much as you
can money
see money doesn't buy you happiness
but what money offers you is freedom
money is freedom
and
money is power money gives you the power
to do whatever you want with your time
the freedom to do whatever with you you
want to do with your time so the correct
way to enjoy money
is to keep it in your bank account or
keep it invested somewhere in the right
places
the moment you spend it it's gone
your power is gone your freedom is gone
so stop buying useless things stop
buying things you don't need stop buying
a expensive phone every year
i buy a phone once in four years i buy
the reasonably cheap phone i don't buy
very expensive phones what's the need
for that you don't need that don't buy
things you don't need to impress people
you don't like
don't buy expensive branded clothes 2000
rupees 3000 rupees whatever stop wasting
money
save money invest money so how much of
your monthly income should you should
you save well if you are a starter
if you're starting off in your
journey
so let's say you are in college or
university and you are doing some
part-time job to have some extra income
maybe you you're earning 10 15 000
rupees for a few hours of work every
week every week you should save all of
it save all of it or invest all of it
if you have your first full-time job
maybe you're earning for 30 50 000
rupees a month hypothetically
so that is not a lot of money let's say
you are a beginner
your first job offers you 50 let's say
30 000 rupees
that's how it goes for many people
so if you're earning just 30 000 rupees
you will have your rent to take care of
your in your expenses food clothing all
that so not a lot will be left behind
so in that case if your income is less
then try to save at least 20 of it so
what is 20 of 30 000 rupees it's
6 000 rupees
i'm sure anybody can save that so save
that invested or whatever
if you are earning one lakh
a month
you can easily save 40 or 50 of it
invest it somewhere if you're earning 10
lakh a month
i'm sure you can save 90 of it so the
more your income rises the more you will
be able to save
save it don't waste money on useless
things of course you should have some
fun go go to
restaurant once in a while hang on with
your friends have a party once a week or
whatever works for you
but don't
have a habit of wasting money
unnecessarily it's not going to buy you
any happiness
it's just a temporary rush there is this
this
concept right of uh
what are they called retail therapy
you're not feeling good you're feeling
unhappy go go do a lot of shopping go
spend a few thousand rupees you'll feel
better you'll feel better for a few
minutes once you come back home you'll
feel terrible you wasted so much money
and you bought all the stuff you don't
need
so things don't buy you happiness
freedom buys you happiness
let's say you have one crore rupees in
your bank account
and you have invested all of that in
getting let's say 10 returns per year 10
returns per year of one crore rupees is
10 lakh rupees you can live a very
comfortable life on 10 lakh rupees a
year
without having to work you can even have
a couple of vacations per year if you
use it wisely
so money is power money is freedom
money will not buy you happiness it
could buy you freedom
so save as much as you can have some fun
enjoy your money but don't waste it
unnecessarily
so depending on how much you earn you
can save more or less
that's the general advice i would give
bibic holder says
what is greater
natural talent or hard work people say
that hard work can surpass talent but i
guess somebody with natural talent can
surpass a hard worker with much less
effort and time
my opinion is very clear
talent is overrated
there is nothing without hard work you
may have you may be the most naturally
talented person in the world if you are
lazy if you are incapable of doing hard
work you will achieve nothing in life
unfortunately
there are so many examples in sport in
sports
of outrageously talented youngsters you
can see they have this incredible talent
but for whatever reason they waste it
and they achieve nothing much
there are so many examples in a variety
of sports whether it is cricket whether
it's football whether it's tennis
whether it's golf or whatever
so many examples of wasted talent and
the major reason is that they got misled
they earned some money and they started
enjoying the high life
or
most likely because they were not
capable of working hard
so there are so many examples of that so
you may be the most talented person in
the world but unless you are willing to
be
really willing to work really hard and
be disciplined and dedicated unless you
have that you will achieve
not much in your life look at the great
champions in tennis roger federer he is
outrageously talented
but there are people who are such a
talent like him they achieve
not much
why was roger federer able to achieve so
much because of his incredible work
ethic because of the hard work that he
put in he would not have won 20 grand
slam titles over all these years had he
not worked so
hard at his game
so talent is just the precondition for
success
but the real condition is the ability to
work really hard to dedicate
weeks months years of your life in the
pursuit of your whatever objectives you
have
so a natural talent is of no use without
the ability and the willingness to work
really really hard
and it's not for everybody not everybody
is made for working very hard so
so most people they want to live
reasonably good lives ordinary
comfortable lives they don't want to
achieve anything great which is
perfectly fine
everybody is different everybody should
achieve what makes them happy
so if you want to have an ordinary happy
normal life if that makes you happy
great that's what we should go for
but some people
want to achieve great things for them
it's not an easy journey
so that's how it is so so in my opinion
talent is good but it is worthless
without the ability to work really
really hard
okay conal says
we see that almost in every religion
there is a story of a great flood the
story of matsuya tarmanu
story of noah's ark story of gilgamesh
story of moses
edmund haley argued it could have been a
causal shock by an impact of a comet i
want to know if there was such a
historical event yeah so it's true that
most of the ancient cultures of the
world whether it's egypt whether it's
india whether it's mesopotamia or the
the
jewish semitic traditions or whatever
all of these cultures have a flood myth
of a story of an ancient flood
now
obviously you can't have a flood that
that encompassed the whole world that
doesn't make sense the thing is most of
the ancient civilizations they were
centered around rivers
without a river there is no civilization
mostly india is a major river valley
civilization
and
similarly in
mesopotamia the story of gilgamesh etc
you have the euphrates and the tigris
rivers
in egypt you have the great nile and so
on and so forth so wherever you have
rivers
from time to time you have big floods so
maybe that is the reason why this
story or this pattern
recurs throughout history and throughout
a variety of cultures maybe that is the
reason why because all of these cultures
were built around great rivers maybe
that's the reason why
maybe there are different floods on
different rivers
so that could be one reason or maybe
there was some global impact global
event that may have caused flooding in
many parts of the world at the same time
possibly
so that is also a possibility that can
be considered
there is this
hypothesized
event about 12 or 13 000 years before
today called the younger dryas event so
it looks like there was some kind of a
extraterrestrial impact event
not a very massive one but something
that definitely did cause
global cooling for a thousand or so
years and maybe it would have caused
some uh flooding as well
so that is
a hypothesis it's a theory it's not been
conclusively proven but it's something
that is
taken more seriously in recent times so
that is a possibility so we don't have
any hard evidence as of today of some
event that would have caused global
flooding in
asia eurasia as well as africa we don't
have any evidences of today but there
are possibilities
so one possibility is a global event a
global impact even like the like the
hypothetical
younger dryas event
or maybe each of these cultures was
founded on major rivers and
every river has a big flood once in a
you know 500 years or thousand years or
something like that so maybe that's the
reason why there are so many
flood stories
kosovo says according to the latest imf
in world bank reports for this financial
year 2022-23
india's gdp is set to grow at 9.2
percent is this a good pace or do we
need to increase it into double digits
for becoming the third largest economy
by 2930
it's a good pace 9.2 is excellent
ideally we want 10 plus but yeah you
know
9 is not bad nobody is going to say 9 is
bad
so i think it's a good rate of growth
the trick is to sustain
this sort of growth for two decades
not one decade but it we need if we need
then we will become a major economy you
know 10 trillion dollar plus
so we need at least eight or nine
percent growth i would say at least
eight percent growth for 20 years
so the trick is not to have a single
year of high growth the trick is to have
sustained high growth over two decades
that is what we need to do so i am very
happy that our economy is going to grow
at 9.2 percent this year it is projected
to grow at this at this rate excellent
we need to find ways of sustaining this
growth and hopefully even increasing it
further
so that is what needs to happen
now please understand that high gdp and
high growth
is a prerequisite for a country becoming
prosperous it's not quite enough
what really is important is if you are
prosperous you need good leadership
so let's say india becomes a 10 trillion
dollar economy is it enough for india to
become a major power superpower not
quite you may be a major economy but if
you are mismanaging your country or
whatever it's not gonna work think about
sports
there are certain certain sports teams
let's talk about the ipl some teams have
a lot of funding lot of money
but they don't necessarily win the title
every year
right so having money is good it's a
prerequisite for growth and achievement
but it's not the only ingredient you
need the right kind of leadership for a
country and for a sports team to become
a genuine power
whether it is the ipl whether it is the
english premier league there are teams
like manchester united liverpool etc who
have bucket loads of money and yet
they're not doing well so please
remember this also it's not enough to
have money
the right leadership is the most
important thing
so india will need
all of these ingredients in the next 20
years to become
a great power which i hope it will
abhishek says do you intend to do
prolonged fasting every year now i've
tried i recently tried multiple
prolonged fasts the longest being one
week long i experienced dizziness
weakness and general fatigue on most
days at no point i felt that energy and
zest that some people talk about when
they fast i measured my parameters as
well my sugar was constantly around 50
post 48 hours of fasting am i doing
something wrong what was your general
experience in terms of how you felt
overall
see i would not recommend prolonged
fasting to anybody without medical
supervision now i have done this thing
multiple times
in the year which year was it 2020
i think it was 21.
in march or so i did a 21 day water fast
only water no calories no food
21 days
then
the same year i think in a few months
later i did a 23 day fast which i
actually put out i did a series of vlogs
on another channel on my other youtube
channel so i fasted for 23 days only
water no food
uh it's about that
this uh this
when was it december was it
yeah the first two fasts were in the
year 2020 this last december i did a 14
day fast i intended it to wear 21 day
fast i broke it off at 14 days so once
again 14 days only water
no calories so i have done this multiple
times without medical supervision maybe
not the smartest thing to do but
i understand my body very well i've had
a lot of experience with it and i always
ensure that i was reasonably
overweight when i started the fast
because you lose weight very fast
so i would not advise anybody to do any
kind of prolonged fasting without
medical supervision and medical advice
i mean everybody's body is different i
have a very robust body i'm physically
well
thanks to the gods i'm reasonably
reasonably physically strong so my body
is able to take it i did not measure my
sugar or anything the only parameters i
measured my where my weight
my blood pressure and my
pulse rate that's the only parameters i
measured as long as that was fine i kept
on doing the fasting and i overall felt
good
i did not experience
major dizziness weakness or fatigue
uh throughout the thing i actually felt
great when i was fasting i felt mentally
very clear
great mental clarity physically your
strength decreases no doubt about it if
you don't eat i mean if you don't eat
for 14
20 to 3 weeks your physically so your
physical strength will decrease
your muscle mass will shrink i've
experienced that every single time so
there are effects of fasting
but uh i did feel
a great amount of mental clarity
energy as well
so you can feel energetic without being
physically strong you can right so you
lose muscle mass you lose weight
you become physically weaker but you
feel more energetic that is my
experience
so i don't know what is how it is going
for you everybody's body is different
everybody's background is different your
genetics are different your metabolism
is different your food habits are
different there's so many parameters
that goes into all of this so i'm not
sure if you're doing anything wrong or
right
my general experience
has always been great i've always loved
it i will do it again in the future
but i would
uh
issue a word of strong caution i would
advise nobody to do this without first
consulting a good doctor and being
through
uh throughout super supervised by a good
doctor that's the safest way of doing
this
spur seagull says what's the difference
between a vasal state and a colony is
the latter a harsher term than the
former
as it represents slavery slavery loot
plunders that india suffered for eight
centuries in this context are japan uk
germany etc was all states of the us or
are they pure colonies need your opinion
okay very good
a colony
is a country
or a nation
or a geographical region
where a more powerful country comes
and indulges in extraction of wealth
and treasure
and maybe they take over the land and
they settle their own people there look
at north america it's a colony of the
europeans
they went to north america settled down
there
massacred the natives
most likely about 100 million natives
were massacred over a couple of
centuries
or three four centuries maybe
and they have stolen the entire land
that's a colony
so that is settler
colonialism they settled there that they
stole the land in the case of india
india was a colony of the uk of the
british
they did not quite settle down in india
but they extracted everything of value
out of india they enriched themselves at
our expense they destroyed india's
economy india's econ industries
everything in india and they extracted
more than 45 trillion dollars worth of
wealth and treasure out of india and
that's why the west is so prosperous
that is colony that is colonization a
vasal state
is not a colony a wasall state is a
nation or a country or whatever or a
kingdom
that is
subordinate to your kingdom
but you don't extract wealth you don't
destroy the land you don't you don't
plunder the country they are subordinate
to you they give you a certain amount of
tax per year
or what do they call it they call it um
i'm not sure i don't remember the term
for it
tribute they pay you tribute every year
and they acknowledge you as their
suzerain as their overlord and whenever
you tell them to do certain things they
will do it for you
let me give you
an example
about 1200 or so years before today
the vikings
were plundering europe they were
plundering
they were raiding and plundering
the uk the british islands
and also western europe western france
etc
and one of these major
raiders was a guy a viking called rollo
rollo
so this guy would come and plunder the
uk the british islands and even western
france repeatedly year after year
so eventually the king of france he
offered rollo a deal
he said
i will offer you a
huge amount of land in north western
france you and your men will settle down
in this territory which belongs to me
you will settle down there
and you will rule it as if you are the
kings so roller will be the king but you
will be
my
you will be i will be your overlord you
will recognize me as your king so you
will be the duke of this place
and you will have to marry the french
women of the french women and and adopt
the french language and become
christians so that was the deal rollo
accepted that
and he became the first duke of normandy
so normandy this region in northwestern
france
was a de facto
vasal state of france it was part of
france it was ruled by rollo
independently but every year he paid
tribute to the king of france and
whenever the king of france needed
roller to come and fight for him with
his soldiers he would have to come and
fight for him so that is a wasall state
it's not a colony a colony is something
that you'd loot and destroy completely a
vasal state has a certain different role
so there's this subtle difference it's
actually quite unsubtle so that in brief
is the difference between a vasal state
and colony so the us is not plundering
japan
it's not
but it is
japan is very much under the boots of
the us the same goes for germany the
same goes for the uk they do whatever
they are told they don't really have an
independent foreign policy they don't
really have an independent internal
policy also to a certain extent
so that is a vassal state they are not
being plundered actively but they are
subordinate to the us in a variety of
ways that's why i keep saying
that japan south korea the uk germany
etc are u.s masala states they're not
colonies they were solid states
australia may be a colony
okay game loops is how does the mind of
a theoretical physicist work it depends
on the person
so there are certain things
that are common to every theoretical
physical physicist or every scientist
the scientific method you have a very
clear understanding of scientific of the
scientific method what it is
you don't mix up science and
spirituality science and religion you
don't do that as a physicist or as a
scientist so that is something every
scientist has every mathematician also
has this
and
every theoretical physicist has a good
good grasp of
a big range of mathematical tools the
so-called mathematical methods of
physics you need to be good at all of
that so it's like
having a multitude of different skills
and a good theoretical physicist also
has the ability to learn new math on
demand so if i need to solve a problem
but it needs a certain kind of
mathematics that i don't know i should
be able to learn that very quickly maybe
in a couple of days or maybe a week
depending on the magnitude of the
problem you're solving so that is
something that's common to all
theoretical physicists
now um
some but there are two categories of
theoretical physicists and
mathematicians also
so one is the procedural scientist the
other one is the intuitive scientist the
procedural
physicist or the procedural
mathematician will try to solve a
problem by going step by step using the
tool of mathematics step by step you go
progress in the direction slowly slowly
slowly and eventually you solve the
problem that is the procedural
theoretical physicist and the procedural
mathematician but there are a small
there's a small minority of theoretical
physicists and mathematicians who are
not procedural they're intuitive
problem solvers they see the solution
before they
figure out how to do it
so they know what the solution is and
then they spend spend a long time trying
to work out the mathematics of how to
reach the solution in a logical
sequential way
but they
intuitively no answers before they
actually reach there so that is the
small minority of the theoretical
physicists people in mathematicians
people like ramanujan
very intuitive mathematician
someone like john nash
and i'm sure certain
physicists would also fall into this
category people like
maybe albert einstein
maybe somebody else so
so it's a
there are different kinds of scientists
and
the the geniuses typically are the ones
who are intuitive they can see the
solution before they figure out how to
reach the solution so they are the
geniuses they have these flashes of
insight that come from god knows where
ramanujan used to say that it used to
come from his goddess and she used to
come in his dreams and offer him the
equations and then he would write down
the equations when he woke up but he
would not quite know how to
offer how to work out the proof of the
equations and then it would take him
time to work out the proof of the
equations but he would get the equation
before they actually
knew how to work the proof
so that's a highly intuitive
mathematician or scientist those are the
geniuses
okay alpha says what will be our future
most probably be like will it be
dystopian will it be high-tech will it
be mingled with nature
well i hope it is high-tech and mingled
with nature with nature dystopian future
is the worst possible thing pollution
destroyed environment deforestation
or oceans and rivers full of plastic
that's a dystopian future and big data
big brother rooting over us
a global government
yeah
digital slavery
so that is a dystopian future when when
humanity has lost all free will
we are slaves to the algorithm
we are all hooked to the metaverse
sitting in a dark corner of some room
but we think we are doing great things
that is a dystopian future i hope we are
not going in the direction we are
actually going in the direction i hope
there is a course correction at some
point in time in the near future
what i would like to see
is a high-tech future mingled with
nature
nature is very important if we destroy
nature there is no future
i would like to see nature re-emerge
again
you know
i would like to see more forests more
greenery i would also like to see high
technology
and
you know in the 1950s and 60s the
science fiction writers had imagined
worlds in which
technology had solved all the problems
of the world and nobody had to work
anymore and people would go after
creative pursuits without having to work
and having to earn
so that was the utopian future they had
imagined today we are going towards a
dystopian future so i hope
that we have a high-tech future which is
mingled with nature
but unfortunately we are going in the
wrong direction we are going towards a
dystopian future if you look at all the
science fiction movies and novels that
you see today all talk about a dystopian
world which is terrible so i hope that
doesn't happen
uh asha says you said the batman movie
was depressing in your opinion can you
name any optimistic movie you can
recommend and do you follow any director
like nolan or quentin tarantino etc
uh
yeah i thought the batman movie was
depressing and the strange thing the
funny thing is that so many people got
upset about that
i got so many of these comments where
people were angry and upset
why do you get upset why do you react
emotionally
you don't have to agree with me if you
liked the movie great good for you i did
not like it
we can agree to disagree there's no need
to get upset about it or get angry about
me not liking a certain movie i did not
like it i found it very depressing dark
i don't like it at all
so and and it's not like
i don't i it's not like i dislike all
dark movies there are certain movies
that are really well made i can think of
an example the ring
it's a horror movie from the early 2000s
it was incredibly dark
very somber
it was kind of depressing but it was a
really well made movie i liked the movie
but i did not like the feeling it it uh
the
emotions it evokes
in you
it's atmospheric horror it's not that
physical
gore slasher kind of horror it's
emotional it is it is
atmospheric
horror and psychological horror uh so it
was
it was a very well made movie so um
can i name any optimistic movies that i
can recommend
i can
name lots of movies that i like life is
beautiful by roberto benigni i think
it's from 97 or something
1997 or something i think it won the
oscar award for the best foreign movie
or something really good movie very
optimistic positive movie i like
directors like quentin tarantino great
director pulp fiction i like pulp
fiction i like fight club the good the
bad and the ugly by sergio leone
uh the matrix star wars interstellar
a dark movie like seven really well made
i like movies like the terminator
predator kona and the barbarian
uh japanese movies by directors like
akira kurosawa the seven samurai yojimbo
kage musha i'm sure most of you have not
heard of that
then war movies i don't mind war movies
apocalypse now
detective stories
mystery stories the usual suspects
the godfather alien lord of the rings
forest gump a very positive movie
and then
leon the professional the fifth element
die hard movies by charlie chaplin like
modern times the great dictator uh city
lights
then alfred hitchcock
vertigo a war movie like
das booth a german movie and so on so as
you can see most of my influences are
from outside india that's how i grew up
that's the influences i absorbed
and i can't i've also watched lots of
indian movies but i can't quite think of
any really good movies from bollywood or
whatever
i liked baahubali in recent times it was
good i liked that
older bollywood movies were nice but
then i found out many of them were
plagiarized this either the story was
plagiarized or the songs were
plagiarized and that kind of leaves a
bad taste in your mouth
so
yeah
there were there are certainly some very
good indian movies
and a lot of good music also from older
movies
today's movies from from bollywood are
mostly trash mostly garbage so i just
avoid that i don't watch anymore
so
so that's what i can say i like certain
directors like quentin tarantino i think
all of his movies are really stylish
very good stories and very very
very good way of telling a story i like
christopher nolan as well and there are
many other directors directors that i
like i'm sure i've missed out a lot of
these
movies and directors i like but
just a small sample so to say
okay
um
creeper says
uh
this is a question from my daughter due
to relativity if two objects are going
at sixty percent of the speed of light
relative to me and going in opposite
directions would they be going at 120
percent of the speed of light relative
to each other
since nothing goes beyond the speed of
light what would actually happen so from
your perspective it would feel like they
are going at 120 percent of the speed of
light in opposite direction only from
your perspective if you go into the
reference frame of either of these two
objects
and you apply the lawrence
transformations which you can look up
then i believe it will come out to be
about about 80 85 percent of the speed
of light relative to each other but
relative to you the observer at the
midpoint
it will appear to you like they are
going in opposite direction that 120
percent of the speed of light but only
relative to you it's an illusion
from either of their perspectives from
their reference frames it's going to be
about
i think if you do the calculations it's
about 80 85
somewhere there of the speed of light so
if you have two protons going in
opposite directions that's the kind of
relativistic effect you will observe
and you can calculate that very easily
very quickly using the lawrence lawrence
transformations
so that's what i can see
um
rishi says you have often emphasized on
the importance of the sanskrit language
for our culture so how can a youth of
today learn pure sanskrit or build a
successful career in sanskrit
well sanskrit is a bedrock of our
culture
of the entirety of indian culture
uh
so how can a youth of today learn pure
sunshine i have given this book
reference multiple times of sanskrit
sanskrit swayam shikshak it's a book in
hindi not available in english but if
you can read hindi
acquire the book it's a very cheap book
small book and you can
acquire a very good understanding of
sanskrit in just
a couple of months
using that book or can you build a
successful career in it i think there is
a huge demand
among the indian people
for learning sanskrit and there are many
youtube channels that do a very poor job
of teaching sanskrit
learning a language should be really
easy but only if the teacher knows how
to teach it properly i see most of these
channels i'm not naming names i'm sure
there are some good ones as well but
most of the channels i've seen that try
to teach sanskrit do it in a very
difficult manner it's not easy to
understand
so if you can
figure out
how to teach sanskrit in a simple manner
i am sure you can make a very profitable
and successful career out of it
so first you will have to learn sanskrit
at a high level of proficiency then you
will have to
acquire the skills of teaching it
effectively if you do that you will have
a good career in sanskrit
okay
let's take a look at some of the
comments or live chat comments
my favorite sci-fi movie is love story
2015 never heard of it but let's look it
up
okay do you have any questions if you
have questions i will do a few minutes
of live chat questions comments
go ahead ask me
let's see
what's the secret of your hair vijay
vagila says there's no secret just don't
cut it let it let it go there you have
it see i have not cut it for two more
than two years i think the last time i
cut my hair i had a haircut was in
august i believe 20
so it's gonna be three years and you can
see it grows slowly
so just don't cut your hair let it go
let it go wild so that's the secret
wash it reasonably frequently
and that's all there's no the secret
all right what else do we have
originally are we humans veg or non-veg
i think originally all animals
see all food is the predation of other
living beings beings
so i believe in the past let's say if
you go back 66 million years before
today
to the time of the deccan traps
volcanism and the chick-fil-a impact
event our ancestors were small
rat like creatures
very small mammals that survived this
horrible
impact event so i believe that in order
to survive they they were forced to eat
whatever they could find
maybe they had to eat the remains of
other dinosaurs or something like that
so eventually
if you go back far enough you will have
non-vegetarian carnivorous ancestors but
in india
in our culture we had this great
subcontinent
very fertile
very rich subcontinent so many resources
so it became unnecessary to kill animals
in order to sustain yourself there was
so much vegetation
such fertile soil that you do not have
to kill animals and that's how i think
we
our ancestors preferred
overall
to become vegetarian but indians at
least some indians at all times have
been
non-vegetarian so
that's just how it has been for us
what food do you like
i love all kinds of food yeah wherever i
go i want to try the local food
you know
so i i love traveling i love love
traveling across the country across the
world and where whichever new place i go
to i would like i always like to eat the
local food
i like to interact with the local people
i love
variety
you know some people they enjoy they
they like sameness they want to be
people who speak the same language or
the same beliefs as them and with the
same food as them i am the opposite of
that i like to i like variety i like
traveling i like interacting with people
who speak different languages who have
different backgrounds and i like to try
a variety of different cuisines so i
like all kinds of cuisines i think every
country every culture has some
interesting
something interesting to contribute in
terms of cuisine so i i like everything
i like uh to try new things
okay
karan nalawat says what is the speed of
light it's roughly 300 000 kilometers
per second three lakh kilometers per
second roughly slightly less than that
but if you want an approximate answer
three lakh kilometers per second that is
the speed of light
okay
kinchuk says can you please tell why
india is not making
the asian
sato ato asian treaty organization like
nato to counter china with asian
countries which is really threatened by
china in order to create such a
confederation or alliance you need to be
really powerful
and you need to be
other countries will come into such an
anti-china organization only if they are
confident that you will be able to
protect them against anything that that
china does to them
today
india is not in a position to offer that
sort of
immunity to other countries
in case china does some kind of harm to
them
so for india to be able to create an
organization like this india will first
have to become a major
asian power india is already a major
asian power but a genuine hard power
like able to stand up to china
economically and militarily as an equal
right now india is not an equal
so it will happen
maybe in the future as of today india is
not
powerful enough to
do that
all right where are we what else do we
have um
can china stop ganga and brahmaputra
river water i think the ganga originates
somewhere in the himalayas
or not in chinese occupied territory
most likely
and the brahmaputra for sure comes from
tibet which is occupied by china the
thing is this
let's take a look at the map where's the
map i have to open them in
let's take a look at the map of india
and
and see what
the brahmaputra
river is like so let's open the
satellite imagery
oh look at that
so the brahmaputra comes via arunachal
pradesh and comes into assam and goes
all the way down that's how it is it
originates in tibet but
where is the river
where is the great river the brahmaputra
here it is
as you can see
the majority of this river
originates in the forests of arunachal
pradesh if you go north it's just a thin
trickle
so the truth is that more than 80
percent of the water of the brahmaputra
river
originates in rainfall that falls
in the forested regions of arunachal
pradesh
so even if china were to cut off all the
water to the brahmaputra from tibet the
brahmaputra would still not be affected
majorly because
the majority of the river of this of the
water of this river originates in india
itself
so the chinese even if they try
they can't do much about this and the
ganga i think it does not originate in
chinese occupied territory which means
we are fine
so don't worry too much about that
current says what are quark stars so
quark stars
quark stars are stars that are
hypothetical stars
that are made up of this exotic
matter called quark matter
so when you compress uh
you have we have these stars called
neutron stars which are giant atomic
nuclei about 10 kilometers or so in
diameter and they are mainly
made up of neutrons only
now if you compress such a star even
further then you would have a
quark matter
forming
in the interior of the star
so in which case the quarks will no
longer be confined and they will be free
to move around in this big soup of
quarks so that's a hypothetical form of
matter it's never been observed
and maybe some of the stars we consider
to be neutron stars may actually be
quark stars on the interior having a
shell of neutron matter on the exterior
so that's a hypothetical kind of star
it's never been really observed
that's a quark star made of quarks a
a sea of deconfined quarks in the inside
okay
captain stark says what are
mahajanapadas they don't exist anymore
they were the great republics of india
i think there were 14 of them
was it 14
yeah a number of
independent republics mahajanapadas in
ancient india
they were
democratic republics
so that in grief is what the
mahajanapadas were
and this era came to an end about about
roughly 2000 or so years before today
all right
some other questions let me see
am i an alien no i i don't know maybe
what's going on in myanmar it's hard to
tell it's a closed off country
it's again ruled by the military it's
been ruled out by the military for many
decades maybe there's some chinese
interference there now so we don't quite
know what's happening there and there is
very little government to government
connection now between india and myanmar
of course we have a significant
land border with myanmar
if you look here where's the border
as you can see mizoram manipur nagaland
and arunachal pradesh
have a shared border with myanmar but
that's a very extensive border and yet
we have very little people-to-people
connection there must be some local
connection over there in the
northeastern part of india the far east
of india
especially a variety of tribes that
don't quite recognize the boundaries
which is fine
but we don't know what's happening
politically there the army the military
junta is in power but they are very
secretive so it's quite opaque
what's happening there the situation is
opaque
okay
um
what got you interested in history just
curiosity
i was always curious about about the
world
and
i found history to be to some extent
even more interesting than fiction
reading fiction or reading novels
so
i was interested in that from a very
young age
right um
what was the fate of indians who were
sold to slavery by the turks
well
that's never been studied by our
by our historians
but you can guess
because lots of people in central asia
in the various arabic countries in yemen
for instance lots of india lots of
people look like indians
why is that
so obviously the indians who were sold
into slavery many of most of them were
women and children
so i think it's not hard to guess what
happened to them
all right let's take a couple more
questions
what is best for india or pakistan that
is constantly in civil war or pakistan
that is divided into different nations
a pakistan that is divided into nations
sindh balochistan
maybe maybe separate
punjab i think that is better for for
for everybody even from the pakistani
people right now they are ruled by this
army
this tyrannical undemocratic force
called the pakistani army and the
pakistani army is a mercenary force
they don't care about the country they
don't care about the people who they're
supposed to serve they only care about
enriching themselves all that children
live abroad they have
big bank accounts in london mostly
they have big palatial homes in other
countries
and they have been serving whatever
master was has been willing to pay the
money in the past it was the us
that did that for the longest time
now it is china
maybe now they want to go back to the us
so
the army does not serve pakistan the
army serves themselves
and it is best for the people of
pakistan
if the army is to be dismantled and
each of these provinces in the
balochistan
punjab
past
they either ruled themselves
independently or maybe pasta can go back
to
being part of afghanistan if they so
wish so that is best for india
because the terrorism
that india has suffered for from for so
many decades it has come from the
pakistani army
and that terrorism has affected the
people of pakistan as well
so the root cause of all the problems is
the pakistani army it has to be
dismantled hopefully soon
right um
any other interesting
questions
har shiraj saying jala says what's your
take on the previous band against royal
supreme court judgment in favor
not quite sure about that i think the
indian government banned the preview
purses to the
uh that were
given to the royals so i think the
agreement was that the the
the various so-called princely states
who were essentially puppets of the
british
they they agreed to become part of india
in exchange for retaining some sort of
privileges and getting some sort of
money the privy purse from the
government of india
and then it was
taken away from them against the
in in breach of the agreement
and was there a supreme court judgment
in its favor i'm not quite sure i
haven't looked into this so that's what
i know that's the little i know about
this i'm sorry i cannot answer the
question in detail because i am not
aware of the details
maybe in the next in a subsequent
episode i will look this up and maybe i
can answer that in in better detail in
the future but good question very
interesting
okay let me oh it's already 2 hours 12
minutes
let us
books to understand geopolitics from
scratch i have not studied geopolitics
from a single book my understand of
understanding of geopolitics comes from
my study of history
because history is the study of
causality
and if you study history in depth
and from different the world then you
get a very good understanding of what
the cause and effect chain is like why
do things happen we know things happen
things happen all the time but why do
they happen
why do certain things happen and why do
certain things not happen it's all
causality
and geopolitics is all about causality
it's all about the understanding of
power national interest
and causality
so if you study history you understand
that so i don't know of any book about
geopolitics i'm sure there are some
textbooks of geopolitics i'm sure
they're terrible
so the best way to understand
geopolitics is to have a good
understanding of world history
okay
i live in germany deutschland prices are
going up war and indonesia how worse
could it guess could it get
prices are going to go up and the price
rise is permanent unfortunately
uh
germany i mean the whole of europe
was getting was getting this cheap
energy from russia and now it's not
happening
the russians are demanding payment in
rubles
and the various nations that are under
the thumb of the us are refusing that
and now the energy is drying up the gas
is no longer flowing
so the governments including in germany
are asking the people to use less energy
don't use the heat don't keep the heater
on all the time
and so on and so forth
and when there is a scarcity of energy
the prices of all essentials go up
this is going to be a long-term change
it may be a permanent change
so that's just how it is
this is the cause and effect chain of
geopolitics
the causal change that binds the past to
the present to the future
so uh i hope it doesn't get worse
and it's going to affect the whole world
not just germany not just europe it's
going to affect the whole world
energy is overall going to get more
expensive
there's going to be some kind of
scarcity of foods
foodstuffs etc the ukraine and wheat is
not going to be available for some time
and so on and so forth so there's going
to be a big domino effect of the
situation in ukraine i hope it doesn't
get too bad
but
things the changes that are that we are
seeing here
seeing right now they are here to stay
at least for the time being
all right all right
um
anything else
let's see if there is any other
interesting question
prima doctrine
not sure what that is maybe i should
look it up sounds like an interesting
name the primark of doctrine
um
are the mutations in corona virus
stopped why is it going away it's not
stopped
a virus keeps mutating and the more a
virus mutates the less dangerous it
becomes to its host
so
so the newer mutations are going to keep
happening but it's going to be
progressively less dangerous
for
us we are the host
the real reason it's not going it's
going away it seems to be going away is
that because the media is not talking
about it anymore
the media has a other bigger fish to fly
right now like the ukraine crisis and
other things when ukraine becomes the
situation cools down they will try to
bring back that
costly person dr fauci or somebody
so
it's there but it's not going to be a
big problem it was it was never a hugely
dangerous virus in the first place
are you charvaka or vedantis or anything
else i'm certainly not not charvaka
i am not charvaka for sure
okay i think that brings us to the end
of today's session it's one of the
longest ones i've done so far so great
session great questions thank you so
much thank you once again from for for
bringing this show the ask a budget show
to episode 100 and we'll just keep going
and as you know i have made the
announcement i have one month to go for
that so wish me luck thank you everybody
thank you so much
very grateful
and i will see you in the next episode
episode 101 until then take care
good